Essence of set theory
Chapter 1
Introduction
"Set theory has a dual role in mathematics. In pure mathematics, it is the place where questions about infinity are studied.
'Although this is a fascinating study of permanent interest, it does not account for the importance of set theory in applied areas.
There, the importance stems from the fact that set theory provides an incredibly versatile toolbox for building mathematical models of various phenomena."
Hi, and welcome to Essence of set theory!
Because the video targets an audience as diverse and broad as I can get, let's first outline what it's all about.
Set theory, which in Czech is sometimes humorously slang abbreviated as TeMno ('darkness'),
is a mathematical discipline founded in the nineteenth century by George Cantor.
At its core, set theory is the study of infinity;
or rather, infinite sets, to be precise.
If you have ever heard some cool things about infinity,
like how an infinite number of buses each with an infinite amount of people
can fit into a single hotel with an infinite number of rooms,
or how an infinite number of prisoners wearing colored hats
are able to coordinate their actions such that almost all of them can, correctly,
guess their own hat color,
you'll find that these are, indeed, things strongly connected to set theory.
To be honest, understanding infinity is actually
the main reason why we study set theory:
to a mathematician, infinity is beautiful!
It is a concept that provides to a mathematician a whole, amazing world just for the sake of his ideas.
Of course, that means if you're a practically oriented person
who wants to see its direct applications in the real world, sorry;
You won't meet infinity walking down the street.
Still,
there is also another reason why set theory is important:
it gives a solid framework for mathematics in general.
As it turns out, following our intuitions about infinity
can easily lead to paradoxes,
as when a set being an element of itself implies it can't be itself
(is it a paraphrase of Russell's Paradox? I couldn't understand)
Mathematicians had to develop a formal axiomatic framework
to deal with these problems.
And it turned out that their solution was so universal
that it covers virtually any mathematical field.
Therefore set theory actually plays two roles in mathematics:
not only is it the theory of infinity,
but it also constitutes the very foundations of mathematics.
In the first few videos, we'll start with some intuition for infinity;
Then we'll use that intuition to present the problems
and to solve them by introducing a framework in terms of a few axioms;
And we'll finish with some more advanced tools of set theory,
like the principle of maximality.
To begin thinking about infinity, we first have to define it.
What do we mean by a rotated number eight?
Actually, this question is too vague for us to answer. We won't even use the infinity symbol in this series!
Instead, we'll try to define "infinite size":
what's something infinitely big?
Of course, there's a cheap answer:
something infinitely big is something not finitely big.
But "finitely big" is easy to define:
a finitely big set is just a set where its number of elements
can be expressed as a natural number.
A set of five elements is finite.
A set of one million elements is finite too.
But the set of all natural numbers
is too big to be measured by a finite natural number.
Therefore, it is infinite in size.
Even an empty set is finite:
it has zero elements!
That's why we consider zero as a natural number.
This may be somewhat unusual in other fields, but in set theory, it turns out to be...
*very natural*
According to this definition of infinite sets,
in which we defined what infinite definitely isn't,
the answer to our question is that the size of something infinitely big can't just be a large natural number.
Actually, the whole study of infinity
rely on the fact that infinite sets behave in unexpected ways,
and this is precisely what our studies are concerned with.
Consider the following problem:
We have a grid of size five by five
and we are coloring it using two colors, yellow and blue.
If we color it in such a way that all the rows are predominantly blue,
it may happen that some of the columns are predominantly yellow,
but definitely not all of them!
Even if we change the remaining columns so that they are predominantly yellow,
we will unavoidably break some of the grid's rows.
It is really an impossible task to carefully choose grid colors
in such a configuration in which the all the rows are predominantly blue
and, at the same time, all the columns are predominantly yellow.
This happens for the simple reason that we cannot fill the table in such a way
that there are more blue squares than yellow ones
at the same time there are more yellow squares than blue ones!
But what if we pick an infinite grid?
In this case, there exists a colorization of the grid
such that every row contains only a finite number of yellow squares,
and every column contains only a finite number of blue ones.
I recommend you to pause the video and think about it for a while.
You can take your paper and pencil for help.
Here it comes the solution:
Do you see?!
Every row is mostly blue and contains only a finite number of yellow squares
and every column is mostly yellow and contains only a finite number of blue squares.
The impossible task in the finite world
just became possible for the infinite grid.
And that is just the beginning.
In the next chapter...
We will learn how to compare sizes of infinite
sets.
See you then!